<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<nlmSearchResult>
  <term>cardiovascular+disease</term>
  <file>viv_DEV3NY</file>
  <server>pvlb7srch15</server>
  <count>8</count>
  <retstart>0</retstart>
  <retmax>10</retmax>
  <list num="8" start="0" per="10">
    <document rank="0" url="https://medlineplus.gov/heartdiseases.html">
      <content name="title">Heart Diseases</content>
      <content name="organizationName">National Library of Medicine</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Cardiac Diseases</content>
      <content name="altTitle">&lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;Cardiovascular Diseases&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content>
      <content name="FullSummary">What is heart disease?&lt;p&gt;Heart disease is a general term that includes many types of heart problems. It's also called &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;cardiovascular disease&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, which means &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;heart and blood vessel disease&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heart disease is the leading cause of death in the United States, but there are ways to prevent and manage many types of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;What are the types of heart disease?&lt;p&gt;There are many different types of heart disease. Some you may be born with, called congenital heart disease. Other types develop during your lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coronary artery disease (also called coronary heart disease) is the most common type of heart disease. It happens slowly over time when a sticky substance called plaque builds up in the arteries that supply your heart muscle with blood. The plaque narrows or blocks blood flow to the heart muscle and can lead to other heart problems:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Angina - chest pain from lack of blood flow&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heart attacks - when part of the heart muscle dies from loss of blood flow&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heart failure - when your heart can't pump enough blood to meet your body's needs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Arrhythmia - a problem with the rate or rhythm of your heartbeat&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other types of heart diseases may affect your heart valves or heart muscle (cardiomyopathy).&lt;/p&gt;What causes heart diseases?&lt;p&gt;The causes of heart disease depend on the type of disease. Some possible causes include lifestyle, genetics, infections, medicines, and other diseases.&lt;/p&gt;Who is more likely to develop heart diseases?&lt;p&gt;There are many different factors that can make you more likely to develop heart disease. Some of these factors you can change, but others you cannot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Age. Your risk of heart disease goes up as you get older.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sex. Some factors may affect heart disease risk differently in women than in men.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Family history and genetics. A family history of early heart disease raises your risk of heart disease. And research has shown that some genes are linked to a higher risk of certain heart diseases.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Race/ethnicity. Certain groups have higher risks than others.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lifestyle habits. Over time, unhealthy lifestyle habits can raise your risk heart disease: 
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Eating a diet high in saturated fats, refined carbohydrates, and salt.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Not getting enough physical activity.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Drinking too much alcohol.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Smoking and exposure to secondhand smoke.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Too much stress.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Having other medical conditions can raise your risk of heart diseases. These conditions include:
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;High blood pressure.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;High cholesterol levels.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Diabetes.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Obesity.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Autoimmune and inflammatory diseases.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Chronic kidney disease.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Metabolic syndrome.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;What are the symptoms of heart disease?&lt;p&gt;Your symptoms will depend on the type of heart disease you have. You may not have symptoms at first. In some cases, you may not know you have heart disease until you have a complication such as a heart attack.&lt;/p&gt;How are heart diseases diagnosed?&lt;p&gt;To find out if you have heart disease, your health care provider will:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ask about your medical history, including your symptoms&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ask about your family health history, including relatives who have had heart disease&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do a physical exam&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Likely run heart tests and blood tests&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In some cases, your provider may refer you to a cardiologist (a doctor who specializes in heart diseases) for tests, diagnosis, and care.&lt;/p&gt;What are the treatments for heart disease?&lt;p&gt;Treatment plans for heart disease depend on the type of heart disease you have, how serious your symptoms are, and what other health conditions you have. Possible treatments may include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heart-healthy lifestyle changes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Medicines&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Procedures or surgeries&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cardiac rehabilitation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Can heart diseases be prevented?&lt;p&gt;You may be able to lower your risk of certain heart diseases by making heart-healthy lifestyle changes  and managing any other medical conditions you have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NIH: National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      <content name="mesh">Heart Diseases</content>
      <content name="groupName">Older Adults</content>
      <content name="groupName">Blood, Heart and Circulation</content>
      <content name="snippet"> ... many types of heart problems. It's also called &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;cardiovascular disease&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, which means &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;heart and blood vessel disease. Heart&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  ... </content>
    </document>
    <document rank="1" url="https://medlineplus.gov/vasculardiseases.html">
      <content name="title">Vascular Diseases</content>
      <content name="organizationName">National Library of Medicine</content>
      <content name="altTitle">&lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;Cardiovascular Diseases&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Circulatory Disorders</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Hemangioma</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Veins</content>
      <content name="FullSummary">What are vascular diseases?&lt;p&gt;Your vascular system is your body's network of blood vessels. It includes your:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Arteries, which carry oxygen-rich blood from your heart to your tissues and organs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Veins, which carry the blood and waste products back to your heart&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Capillaries, which are tiny blood vessels that connect your small arteries to your small veins. The walls of the capillaries are thin and leaky, to allow for an exchange of materials between your tissues and blood.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vascular diseases are conditions which affect your vascular system. They are common and can be serious. Some types include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Aneurysm - a bulge or "ballooning" in the wall of an artery&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Atherosclerosis - a disease in which plaque builds up inside your arteries. Plaque is made up of fat, cholesterol, calcium, and other substances found in the blood.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Blood clots, including deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Coronary artery disease and carotid artery disease, diseases that involve the narrowing or blockage of an artery. The cause is usually a buildup of plaque.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Raynaud phenomenon - a disorder that causes the blood vessels to narrow when you are cold or feeling stressed&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stroke - a serious condition that happens when blood flow to your brain stops.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Varicose veins - swollen, twisted veins that you can see just under the skin&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Vasculitis - inflammation of the blood vessels&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;What causes vascular diseases?&lt;p&gt;The causes of vascular diseases depend on the specific disease. These causes include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Genetics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heart diseases such as high cholesterol and high blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Infection&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Injury&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Medicines, including hormones&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the cause is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;Who is at risk for vascular diseases?&lt;p&gt;The risk factors for vascular diseases can vary, depending on the specific disease. But some of the more common risk factors include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Age - your risk of some diseases goes up as you get older&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Conditions that can affect the heart and blood vessels, such as diabetes or high cholesterol&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Family history of &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;vascular or heart diseases&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Infection or injury that damages your veins&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lack of exercise&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Obesity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pregnancy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sitting or standing still for long periods of time&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Smoking&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;What are the symptoms of vascular diseases?&lt;p&gt;The symptoms for each disease are different.&lt;/p&gt;How are vascular diseases diagnosed?&lt;p&gt;To make a diagnosis, your health care provider will do a physical exam and ask about your symptoms and medical history. You may have imaging tests and/or blood tests.&lt;/p&gt;How are vascular diseases treated?&lt;p&gt;Which treatment you get depends on which vascular disease you have and how severe it is. Types of treatments for vascular diseases include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lifestyle changes, such as eating a heart-healthy diet and getting more exercise&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Medicines, such as blood pressure medicines, blood thinners, cholesterol medicines, and clot-dissolving drugs. In some cases, providers use a catheter to send medicine directly to a blood vessel.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Non-surgical procedures, such as angioplasty, stenting, and vein ablation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Surgery&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Can vascular diseases be prevented?&lt;p&gt;There are steps you can take to help prevent vascular diseases:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Make healthy lifestyle changes, such as eating a heart-healthy diet and getting more exercise&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Don't smoke. If you are already a smoker, talk to your health care provider for help in finding the best way for you to quit.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Keep your blood pressure and cholesterol in check&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If you have diabetes, control your blood sugar&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Try not to sit or stand for up long periods of time. If you do need to sit all day, get up and move around every hour or so. If you are traveling on a long trip, you can also wear compression stockings and regularly stretch your legs.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
      <content name="mesh">Vascular Diseases</content>
      <content name="groupName">Blood, Heart and Circulation</content>
      <content name="snippet">What are vascular diseases? Your vascular system is your body's network of blood vessels. It includes your: Arteries, which carry oxygen-rich blood from  ... </content>
    </document>
    <document rank="2" url="https://medlineplus.gov/coronaryarterydisease.html">
      <content name="title">Coronary Artery Disease</content>
      <content name="organizationName">National Library of Medicine</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Arteriosclerosis, Coronary</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Atherosclerosis, Coronary</content>
      <content name="altTitle">CAD</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Coronary Arteriosclerosis</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Coronary atherosclerosis</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Coronary heart disease</content>
      <content name="FullSummary">&lt;p&gt;Coronary artery disease (CAD) is the most common type of heart disease. It is the leading cause of death in the United States in both men and women.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAD happens when the arteries that supply blood to heart muscle become hardened and narrowed. This is due to the buildup of cholesterol and other material, called plaque, on their inner walls. This buildup is called atherosclerosis. As it grows, less blood can flow through the arteries. As a result, the heart muscle can't get the blood or oxygen it needs. This can lead to chest pain (angina) or a heart attack.  Most heart attacks happen when a blood clot suddenly cuts off the hearts' blood supply, causing permanent heart damage.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, CAD can also weaken the heart muscle and contribute to heart failure and arrhythmias. Heart failure means the heart can't pump blood well to the rest of the body. Arrhythmias are changes in the normal beating rhythm of the heart.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NIH: National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      <content name="mesh">Coronary Artery Disease</content>
      <content name="groupName">Older Adults</content>
      <content name="groupName">Blood, Heart and Circulation</content>
      <content name="snippet"> Coronary artery disease (CAD) is the most common type of heart disease. It is the leading cause of death in the United States in both men and women. CAD happens  ... </content>
    </document>
    <document rank="3" url="https://medlineplus.gov/diabeticheartdisease.html">
      <content name="title">Diabetic Heart Disease</content>
      <content name="organizationName">National Library of Medicine</content>
      <content name="FullSummary">What is diabetes?&lt;p&gt;Diabetes is a disease in which your blood glucose, or blood sugar, levels are too high. Glucose comes from foods you eat. The cells of your body need glucose for energy. A hormone called insulin helps the glucose get into your cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With type 1 diabetes, your body doesn't make insulin. With type 2 diabetes, your body doesn't make or use insulin well. Without enough insulin, glucose builds up in your blood and causes high blood sugar levels.&lt;/p&gt;What is diabetic heart disease?&lt;p&gt;Diabetic heart disease is a term for heart disease in people who have diabetes. If you have diabetes, you are much more likely to develop heart disease or have a stroke than people who don't have diabetes. And you may start having these problems at a younger age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, the effects of high blood sugar from diabetes can include damage to the blood vessels and nerves in your heart. This damage increases your chance of developing heart diseases, including:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Coronary artery disease (CAD). It happens slowly as a sticky material called plaque builds up in the arteries that supply your heart muscle with blood.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heart failure. With this condition, your heart can't pump enough oxygen-rich blood to meet the needs of your body.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cardiomyopathy. This is a group of diseases in which the heart muscle may become thick or stiff.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Who is more likely to develop diabetic heart disease?&lt;p&gt;Diabetes puts you at serious risk for heart disease. It also makes you more likely to develop other conditions that raise your risk even more, including:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;High blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;High blood levels of LDL "bad" cholesterol&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;High triglycerides (a type of fat in your blood) with low blood levels of HDL "good" cholesterol&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your risk for heart disease is also higher if you&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Are male&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Smoke&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Have obesity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Have too much belly fat around your waist, even though you're at a healthy weight:
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For men, that's a waist more than 40 inches&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;For women, that's a waist more than 35 inches&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Have a family history of heart disease&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Have chronic kidney disease&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;What are the symptoms of diabetic heart disease?&lt;p&gt;In the early stages, heart disease usually doesn't have any symptoms. But if your heart disease worsens, you can have symptoms. Your symptoms will depend on the type of heart disease you have. They might include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Shortness of breath&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fatigue&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dizziness or fainting&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Arrhythmia (problem with the rate or rhythm of your heartbeat)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Swollen feet and ankles&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Chest pain&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's important to know that people with diabetes may not feel chest pain. That's because diabetes can damage the nerves in your heart. If you have any symptoms that could be heart disease, talk with your health care provider.&lt;/p&gt;How is diabetic heart disease diagnosed?&lt;p&gt;To find out if you have diabetic heart disease, your provider will:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ask about your medical history, including your symptoms and other health conditions you may have&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ask about your family history, to find out if you have relatives who have or had heart disease&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do a physical exam&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Likely run some tests to help understand your personal risk for heart disease, including:
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Blood tests to check your cholesterol, triglycerides, and blood sugar levels&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A blood-pressure check&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heart tests, if needed&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depending on your risk level, your provider may send you to a cardiologist (a doctor who specializes in heart diseases) for care. If you do have heart disease, treatment will depend on the type of heart disease you have.&lt;/p&gt;How can I prevent diabetic heart disease?&lt;p&gt;You may be able to prevent heart disease or keep it from getting worse by working with your provider to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Control your blood sugar levels&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Manage other conditions you may have that can raise your risk for heart disease &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Take any medicines your provider prescribed&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Make heart-healthy habits part of your daily life&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Follow a healthy eating plan for diabetes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;NIH: National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      <content name="mesh">Diabetes Mellitus</content>
      <content name="mesh">Heart Diseases</content>
      <content name="mesh">Diabetic Cardiomyopathies</content>
      <content name="groupName">Blood, Heart and Circulation</content>
      <content name="groupName">Endocrine System</content>
      <content name="groupName">Diabetes Mellitus</content>
      <content name="snippet">What is diabetes? Diabetes is a disease in which your blood glucose, or blood sugar, levels are too high. Glucose comes from foods you eat. The cells  ... </content>
    </document>
    <document rank="4" url="https://medlineplus.gov/heartdiseaseinwomen.html">
      <content name="title">Heart Disease in Women</content>
      <content name="organizationName">National Library of Medicine</content>
      <content name="FullSummary">What is heart disease?&lt;p&gt;Heart disease is a general term that includes many types of heart problems. It's also called &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;cardiovascular disease&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, which means &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;heart and blood vessel disease&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coronary artery disease (also called coronary heart disease) is the most common type of heart disease in both men and women. It happens slowly over time when a sticky substance called plaque builds up in the arteries that supply your heart muscle with blood. The plaque narrows or blocks blood flow to the heart muscle and can lead to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Angina - chest pain from lack of blood flow&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heart attacks - when part of the heart muscle dies from loss of blood flow&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heart failure - when your heart can't pump enough blood to meet your body's needs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Arrhythmia - a problem with the rate or rhythm of your heartbeat&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;How does heart disease affect women?&lt;p&gt;In the United States, heart disease is the number one cause of death in women. But women are often not diagnosed with heart disease as quickly as men are. That's because:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Women are more likely than men to have "silent" heart disease, meaning that they don't have symptoms.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Health care providers may not recognize heart disease in women because women's symptoms may be different from men's symptoms.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Women are more likely than men to have certain types of heart disease that can be harder to diagnose.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A delay in diagnosis may mean a delay in medical care that could help prevent serious problems, such as a heart attack. That's why it's important to learn about your risk for heart disease, the symptoms in women, and how to keep your heart healthy.&lt;/p&gt;What types of heart disease do women get?&lt;p&gt;Women can get any type of heart disease. Like men, the most common type of heart disease among women is coronary artery disease. But there are certain types of heart disease which are less common, but affect women more often than men:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Coronary microvascular disease - Chest pain from spasms (sudden tightening) in the smallest arteries of the heart that pinch off blood flow. It typically happens during rest or routine activities. This serious condition increases your risk of having a heart attack or other heart diseases.  This type may be harder to diagnose since blockages in smaller arteries can be harder to see on imaging tests.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Broken heart syndrome - Strong chest pain or other signs that look like a heart attack. It's caused by the stress of powerful emotions, such as deep grief, anger, or surprise. It can happen even if you're healthy. It mostly affects women after menopause and usually doesn't cause any lasting damage.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Variant angina - A rare type of strong chest pain from spasms in the heart arteries. The pain usually happens in a pattern during sleep. Variant angina rarely causes a heart attack.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Which women are more likely to develop heart disease?&lt;p&gt;Your risk for developing heart disease increases with:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Menopause. Women can develop heart disease at any age, but your risk increases after your periods stop, usually by age 55. Before menopause, your body makes more estrogen (a female hormone) which helps protect against heart disease. That's why women generally develop coronary artery disease 10 years later than men. During and after menopause, estrogen levels drop and your risk for heart diseases goes up. If your periods stop before age 40, your risk will be higher than other women your age.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Family history of heart disease. Your risk for heart disease may be higher if your:
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mother or sister had heart disease before age 65.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Father or brother had heart disease before age 55.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Problems during pregnancy, such as  high blood pressure, gestational diabetes, anemia, and high blood pressure.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use of hormonal birth control (pills, patches, or vaginal rings with estrogen and progesterone).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Endometriosis.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Polycystic ovary syndrome.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Inflammatory and autoimmune diseases.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Metabolic syndrome.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mental health issues, such as stress, anxiety, or depression.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Health risks from a lack physical activity.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Obesity or being overweight.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Diabetes.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Low HDL cholesterol levels.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mild to moderate high blood pressure.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Smoking.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have one or more risks for heart disease, ask your health care provider for help understanding your risk level. Ask if you need any heart tests to help catch heart disease early.&lt;/p&gt;What are the symptoms of heart disease and heart attack in women?&lt;p&gt;When women have symptoms of heart disease, they may include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pain or discomfort in the chest that may be dull and heavy or sharp&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pain in the neck, jaw, throat, upper belly, or back&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Nausea or vomiting&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Unusual fatigue&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Shortness of breath (feeling like you can't get enough air) during physical activity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women who have coronary artery disease are more likely than men to have chest pain when resting or doing daily activities, rather than during exercise. They're also more likely than men to feel chest pain from mental stress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Symptoms of a heart attack in women may also be different than in men. Chest pain is the most common symptom for both sexes. It may feel like crushing or squeezing. But women are somewhat less likely than men to have chest pain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a heart attack, women may feel:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pressure or tightness in the chest&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pain in the upper back, arms, neck, jaw or throat&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dizziness&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Unusual fatigue&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Indigestion, heartburn, nausea, or vomiting &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stomach pain&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Shortness of breath&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heart attacks usually don't look like the sudden, dramatic events we see in the movies. The symptoms may be mild or strong. They may start slowly. They can stop and then come back.&lt;/p&gt;Can heart disease in women be prevented?&lt;p&gt;You can help lower your risk by:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Learning how to prevent heart disease and making heart-healthy habits part of your daily life.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Asking your provider about your personal risk for heart disease and the best way to manage your heart health.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remember, women can have heart disease without symptoms. But if you pay attention to your risk for heart disease, you can take action to prevent problems or keep them from getting worse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NIH: National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      <content name="mesh">Heart Diseases</content>
      <content name="groupName">Women</content>
      <content name="groupName">Blood, Heart and Circulation</content>
      <content name="snippet"> ... many types of heart problems. It's also called &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;cardiovascular disease&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, which means &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;heart and blood vessel disease. Coronary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  ... </content>
    </document>
    <document rank="5" url="https://medlineplus.gov/latinoandhispanicamericanhealth.html">
      <content name="title">Latino and Hispanic American Health</content>
      <content name="organizationName">National Library of Medicine</content>
      <content name="FullSummary">&lt;p&gt;Every racial or ethnic group has specific health concerns.  Differences in the health of groups can 
result from:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Genetics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Environmental factors&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Access to care&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cultural factors&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this page, you'll find links to health issues that affect Latino and Hispanic Americans.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      <content name="mesh">Hispanic or Latino</content>
      <content name="groupName">Population Groups</content>
      <content name="snippet"> Every racial or ethnic group has specific health concerns.  Differences in the health of groups can 
result from: Genetics  Environmental factors  Access to care   ... </content>
    </document>
    <document rank="6" url="https://medlineplus.gov/metabolicsyndrome.html">
      <content name="title">Metabolic Syndrome</content>
      <content name="organizationName">National Library of Medicine</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Insulin Resistance</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Syndrome X (Metabolic)</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Insulin resistance syndrome</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Metabolic syndrome X</content>
      <content name="FullSummary">What is metabolic syndrome?&lt;p&gt;Metabolic syndrome is the name for a group of risk factors for heart disease, diabetes, and other health problems. You can have just one risk factor, but people often have several of them together. When you have at least three of them, it is called metabolic syndrome. These risk factors include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A large waistline, also called abdominal obesity or "having an apple shape." Too much fat around the stomach is a greater risk factor for heart disease than too much fat in other parts of the body.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Having a high triglyceride level. Triglycerides are a type of fat found in the blood.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Having a low HDL cholesterol level. HDL is sometimes called the "good" cholesterol because it helps remove cholesterol from your arteries.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Having high blood pressure. If your blood pressure stays high over time, it can damage your heart and lead to other health problems.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Having a high fasting blood sugar. Mildly high blood sugar may be an early sign of diabetes.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The more factors you have, the higher your risk for heart disease, diabetes, and stroke is.&lt;/p&gt;What causes metabolic syndrome?&lt;p&gt;Metabolic syndrome has several causes that act together:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Overweight and obesity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;An inactive lifestyle&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Insulin resistance, a condition in which the body can't use insulin properly. Insulin is a hormone that helps move blood sugar into your cells to give them energy. Insulin resistance can lead to high blood sugar levels.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Age - your risk goes up as get older&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Genetics - ethnicity and family history&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;People who have metabolic syndrome often also have excessive blood clotting and inflammation throughout the body. Researchers don't know whether these conditions cause metabolic syndrome or worsen it.&lt;/p&gt;Who is at risk for metabolic syndrome?&lt;p&gt;The most important risk factors for metabolic syndrome are:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Abdominal obesity (a large waistline)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;An inactive lifestyle&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Insulin resistance&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are certain groups of people who have an increased risk of metabolic syndrome:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Some racial and ethnic groups. Mexican Americans have the highest rate of metabolic syndrome, followed by whites and blacks.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;People who have diabetes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;People who have a sibling or parent who has diabetes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Women with polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;People who take medicines that cause weight gain or changes in blood pressure, blood cholesterol, and blood sugar levels&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;What are the symptoms of metabolic syndrome?&lt;p&gt;Most of the metabolic risk factors have no obvious signs or symptoms, except for a large waistline.&lt;/p&gt;How is metabolic syndrome diagnosed?&lt;p&gt;Your health care provider will diagnose metabolic syndrome based on the results of a physical exam and blood tests. You must have at least three of the risk factors to be diagnosed with metabolic syndrome:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A large waistline, which means a waist measurement of 
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;35 inches or more for women&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;40 inches or more for men&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A high triglyceride level, which is 150 mg/dL or higher&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A low HDL cholesterol level, which is
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Less than 50 mg/dL for women&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Less than 40 mg/dL for men&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;High blood pressure, which is a reading of 130/85 mmHg or higher.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A high fasting blood sugar, which is 100 mg/dL or higher&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;What are the treatments for metabolic syndrome?&lt;p&gt;The most important treatment for metabolic syndrome is a heart-healthy lifestyle, which includes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A heart-healthy eating plan, which limits the amount of saturated and trans fats that you eat. It encourages you to choose a variety of nutritious foods, including fruits, vegetables, whole grains, and lean meats.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Aiming for a healthy weight&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Managing stress&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Getting regular physical activity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Quitting smoking (or not starting if you don't already smoke)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If making lifestyle changes is not enough, you may need to take medicines. For example, you may need medicines to lower cholesterol or blood pressure.&lt;/p&gt;Can metabolic syndrome be prevented?&lt;p&gt;The best way to prevent metabolic syndrome is through the heart-healthy lifestyle changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NIH: National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      <content name="mesh">Metabolic Syndrome</content>
      <content name="groupName">Blood, Heart and Circulation</content>
      <content name="groupName">Endocrine System</content>
      <content name="groupName">Metabolic Problems</content>
      <content name="groupName">Diabetes Mellitus</content>
      <content name="snippet">What is metabolic syndrome? Metabolic syndrome is the name for a group of risk factors for heart disease, diabetes, and other health problems. You can  ... </content>
    </document>
    <document rank="7" url="https://medlineplus.gov/smoking.html">
      <content name="title">Smoking</content>
      <content name="organizationName">National Library of Medicine</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Nicotine</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Tobacco Smoking</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Cigar smoking</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Cigarette smoking</content>
      <content name="altTitle">Pipe smoking</content>
      <content name="FullSummary">What are the health effects of smoking?&lt;p&gt;There's no way around it; smoking is bad for your health. It harms nearly every organ of the body, even some that you would not expect. Cigarette smoking causes many cancers and other health problems. It is also the cause of nearly one in five deaths in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of the many health problems that smoking can cause include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cancers. Smoking is the most common cause of lung and oral cancers. But it can also cause cancer in many other parts of your body, such as in your larynx (voice box), esophagus, throat, bladder, kidney, liver, stomach, pancreas, colon and rectum, and cervix. It can also cause acute myeloid leukemia (AML). &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lung diseases. Smoking is the most common cause of COPD. It can also worsen asthma and raise your risk of pneumonia.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;Cardiovascular diseases&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.  Smoking can damage your blood vessels and make them thicken and grow narrower. This makes your heart  beat faster and raises your blood pressure. Smoking also increases your risk of blood clots and stroke.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Vision problems. Smoking can raise your risk of  cataracts and cause macular degeneration (AMD).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;People who smoke while pregnant have a greater chance of certain pregnancy problems.   Their babies are also at higher risk of dying of sudden infant death syndrome (SIDS).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Smoking also causes addiction to nicotine, a stimulant drug that is in tobacco. Nicotine addiction makes it much harder for people to quit smoking.&lt;/p&gt;What are the health risks of secondhand smoke?&lt;p&gt;Your smoke is also bad for other people. If they breathe in your secondhand smoke, they can get many of the same problems as smokers do. These problems can include heart disease and lung cancer. Children exposed to secondhand smoke have a higher risk of ear infections, colds, pneumonia, bronchitis, and more severe asthma. People who breathe secondhand smoke while pregnant are more likely to have preterm labor and babies with low birth weight.&lt;/p&gt;Are other forms of tobacco also dangerous?&lt;p&gt;Besides cigarettes, there are several other forms of tobacco. Some people smoke tobacco in cigars and water pipes (hookahs). These forms of tobacco also contain harmful chemicals and nicotine. Some cigars contain as much tobacco as an entire pack of cigarettes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;E-cigarettes often look like cigarettes, but they work differently. They are battery-operated smoking devices. Using an e-cigarette is called vaping. Researchers still have a lot to learn about the health effects of using e-cigarettes. We do know that they contain nicotine, which is highly addictive and is a health danger for pregnant people, their developing babies, children, and teens. And e-cigarettes also expose non-smokers to secondhand aerosols (rather than secondhand smoke), which contain harmful chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Smokeless tobacco, such as chewing tobacco and snuff, is also bad for your health. Smokeless tobacco can cause certain cancers, including oral cancer. It also increases your risk of getting heart disease, gum disease, and oral lesions.&lt;/p&gt;Why should I quit?&lt;p&gt;Remember, there is no safe level of tobacco use. Smoking even just one cigarette per day over a lifetime can cause smoking-related cancers and premature death. Quitting smoking can reduce your risk of health problems and add years to your life. The earlier you quit, the greater the benefit. Some immediate benefits of quitting include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lower heart rate and blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Less carbon monoxide in the blood (carbon monoxide reduces the blood's ability to carry oxygen)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Better circulation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Less coughing and wheezing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quitting smoking can be challenging, but it is so important for your health. Contact your health care provider if you need help quitting.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      <content name="mesh">Cigarette Smoking</content>
      <content name="mesh">Pipe Smoking</content>
      <content name="mesh">Tobacco Smoking</content>
      <content name="mesh">Water Pipe Smoking</content>
      <content name="mesh">Cigar Smoking</content>
      <content name="groupName">Substance Use and Disorders</content>
      <content name="groupName">Lungs and Breathing</content>
      <content name="snippet"> ... worsen asthma and raise your risk of pneumonia.  &lt;span class="qt0"&gt;&lt;span class="qt1"&gt;Cardiovascular diseases&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.  Smoking can damage your blood vessels and make  ... </content>
    </document>
  </list>
</nlmSearchResult>
